Finding Aid for Joseph A. Gitzen papers, 1917-1919
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joseph A. Gitzen papers 1917-1919
Gitzen, Joseph A.
0.2 linear feet, 1 oversize folder
2010178 Aa 2; UAl
Papers of Corporal Joseph A. Gitzen, resident of Houghton, Mich., member of Co. A., 310th U.S. Engineers who served in the Allied intervention in Russia, 1918-1920, the "Polar Bear Expedition." Collection includes Gitzen's personal and military papers, as well as Company A records, printed materials, maps, and an armband.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Robert Wuthrich (donor no. 10398 ) in August 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
This collection has not been digitized by the Bentley Historical Library.
Resident of Houghton, Mich., who served with Company A, 310th Engineers during the U.S. intervention at Archangel, Russia. Gitzen died between 1958 and 1960.
The Joseph A. Gitzen collection includes Gitzen's diaries, letters and postcards, enlistment cards and field passes, poems and photographs; Co. A rosters and histories; typewritten issues of newsletter The Midnight Sun, newspaper clipping, printed materials, oversize maps, and an armband.
Subjects:
Gitzen, Joseph A.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; United States. Army. Engineer Regiment, 310th. Company A.; Polar Bear Expedition.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Personal files
  The Personal files series contains Gitzen's correspondence, diaries, military papers that include Gitzen's enlistment cards and field passes, two poems (one signed by Gitzen), and five photographs.
  - Correspondence, 1918-1919, undated (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
  - Military papers, 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - Poems, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1918 undated (Box 1)
- U.S. Army 310th Engineers Regiment, Company A records
  The U.S. Army 310th Engineers Regiment, Company A records series contains written histories of the Company and a number of Company rosters.
  - Company A rosters, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Company A histories, 1919 (Box 1)
- Printed materials
  The Printed materials series contains several issues of the typewritten newsletter The Midnight Sun issued aboard of S.S. Steigerwald during the summer 1919 journey from Russia to the United States; a military brochure published by the War Camp Community Service, a song book, and a prayer book.
  - Catholic Prayer Book for the Army and Navy, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Litany of the Saints, undated (Box 1)
  - The Midnight Sun, July 1919 (Box 1)
  - Where Do We Go From Here? [1919 ?] (Box 1)
  - Why Don't You Sing?, undated (Box 1)
- Maps
  The Maps series contains one undated oversize map of Shenkursk and two outsize undated maps of the Archangel region.
  - Sketch of Shenkursk Showing Fortifications, undated (Folder 1)
  - Archangel Government 5th Series, Sheet 1, undated
  - Archangel Government 5th Series, Sheet 2, undated
- Other materials
  The Other materials series contains an undated oversize newspaper clipping from The Daily Mining Gazette listing names of local recruits, and a cloth armband "U.S.A. Badge of Honor."
  - "One Hundred and Sixty Boys of St. Ignatius Congregation in Service of United States," clipping from The Daily Mining Gazette, undated (Folder 1)
  - U.S.A. Badge of Honor, cloth armband